Okay בוקר טוב, boker tov, today's דף daf is נ"ב, nun bet,
מנחות Menachos fifty-two,
and with this we will finish the פרק. perek. We pick up
five lines from the top on the two dots.
תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, and we've been talking about this debate of
Rabbi Shimon and Rabbi Yehuda about whether when there's no כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, is the מנחה mincha brought from the heirs, are they
the ones who pay for it, or is it brought from communal
funds? תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, פר העלם דבר של ציבור Par He’elam
Davar shel Tzibur ושעירי עבודה זרה. u'seirei avodah zarah. So you had
to bring a, what מסכת הוריות Masechet Horayos is devoted to, בית
דין הגדול Beis Din HaGadol ruled incorrectly and most of the community
of עם ישראל Am Yisrael or the people living in Israel followed
them, therefore you bring a special חטאת, chatas, a communal חטאת chatas
called פר העלם דבר של ציבור, Par He’elam Davar shel Tzibur, the
ox of the something that was covered that was you know from
the eyes of the
community, or ושעירי עבודה זרה u'seirei avodah zarah is the case of
when the community sins with עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, so if
these things have happened, where do you get the money to buy
them? They are communal sacrifices, where does that money come from? So
בתחילה מגבין להן, B'techilah magbin lahen, דברי רבי יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda.
Rabbi Yehuda says you do a special collection for them. And you
sort of understand that, you know, the whole ציבור tzibur sinned, you
don't want it just to come from communal funds and people to
be completely oblivious that it's happening, you know, you want them to
connect to the fact that you know we have to bring a
קרבן korban and everybody's gotta chip in for it. רבי שמעון אומר,
Rabbi Shimon omer, Rabbi Shimon says מתרומת הלשכה הן באין. mitrumas halishkah
hein ba’in. No, we'll just use communal regular communal funds that we
collect every year. Okay, now התניא איפכא, ha'tanya ipcha, one minute, we
had a ברייתא braisa that teaches that Rabbi Yehuda and Rabbi Shimon
had the reverse positions. Okay, so rather than saying like one is
wrong, the גמרא'ס Gemara's going to assume that or maybe one is
wrong, we're trying to figure out maybe they reversed their positions or
maybe one is wrong.
הי מינייהו אחריתא? Hai mineihu achrita? Which one of these versions of
who's holding which of this Rabbi Yehuda Rabbi Shimon debate is the
later one, is the reliable one, the final one? So the גמרא
Gemara says אמרו רבנן קמיה דרב אשי, Amru rabanan kamei d'Rav Ashi,
לימא כמעשה אחריתא. leima k'ma'aseh achrita. Let's say the first one we
quoted where Rabbi Shimon says that it is coming from communal funds,
that let's say that is the you know latter one, the authoritative
one. דשמעינן ליה לרבי שמעון דחייש לפשיעה. D'shameinan lei l'Rabbi Shimon d'chayish
l'pshia. We know that Rabbi Shimon is concerned for negligence. How do
we know it? Because Rabbi Shimon says that with the כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol you bring it from communal funds. Now and you don't
want to rely on the heirs. Now maybe that's not a concern
of negligence of the heirs, maybe that's just because it's a פסוק.
pasuk. But the גמרא Gemara just said a minute ago, not a
minute ago, excuse me, like you know on yesterday's דף, daf, it
just said that Rabbi Shimon first had, you know, moved it from
the דאורייתא De’oraisa and had the heirs do it, but because he
was concerned with their negligence or saw their negligence he moved it
back to the דאורייתא. De’oraisa. So because Rabbi Shimon has made a
תקנה takana to move it back to the דאורייתא, De’oraisa, you know
that he is concerned with negligence. And therefore we don't want to
rely on a new collection for these קרבנות, korbanos, and that would
make sense to have him aligned with the position that when it
comes to this פר העלם דבר Par He’elam Davar and so on,
that you bring it from communal funds. Okay, אמר להו רב אשי,
Amar lehu Rav Ashi, אפילו תימא בתרייתא אחריתא. afilu teima basraisa achrita.
No, you can even say that the second ברייתא braisa is the
last one, that by when it comes to פר העלם דבר של
ציבור Par He’elam Davar shel Tzibur Rabbi Shimon would be okay with
collecting funds from everybody. Why? כי קחייש רבי שמעון לפשיעה במידי דלית
ביה כפרה בגוויה. Ki kachayish Rabbi Shimon l'pshia b'milsa d'leisa beh kapara
b'gavah. When is Rabbi Shimon concerned like with the heirs not bringing
the קרבן korban of the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you know, the
מנחה? mincha? That's because they're not being atoned for. It's just an
obligation, obligation, they're shirking their obligation. And he actually witnessed it and
saw it, so he had to move it back to the ציבור.
tzibur. But in this case, you know, first of all this is
just a one-time thing, it's not also regular, that also makes a
difference. במידי דאית ביה כפרה בגוויה, B'milsa d'is beh kapara b'gavah, something
like when the whole ציבור tzibur sins with עבודה זרה avodah zarah
or they sin with this you know that the בית דין Beis
Din and they need atonement, in that type of a thing לא
חייש רבי שמעון לפשיעה. lo chayish Rabbi Shimon l'pshia. He's not concerned
for negligence. Okay, so it's not clear which one is the Rabbi
Shimon, which is the Rabbi Yehuda about how do you collect for
these קרבנות, korbanos, these communal קרבנות. korbanos. מאי הוי עלה? Mai havah
alah? What was the conclusion of this debate, or
or who holds what in this debate? אמר ליה רב זוטא לרב
אשי, Amar lei Rav Zutta l'Rav Ashi, Rav Zutta said to Rav
Ashi, תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear, דתניא, d'tanya, את קרבני
לחמי לאשי ריח ניחוחי תשמרו להקריב לי במועדו. Es korbani lachmi l'ishai
rei'ach nichochi tishmeru l'hakriv li b'mo'ado. This is by the תמיד. Tamid.
My קרבן, korban, my bread for the fire, etc., a lot of
extra words there. Okay, so את לחמי לאשי Es lachmi l'ishai לרבות
פר
העלם דבר של ציבור ושעירי עבודה זרה. l'rabos Par He’elam Davar shel
Tzibur u'seirei avodah zarah. So that is coming to refer to other
things that are communal sacrifices, not just the תמיד, Tamid, and they're
being alluded to in this פסוק pasuk by the תמיד Tamid to
tell you שבאים מתרומת הלשכה דברי רבי שמעון, she'ba'im mitrumas halishkah divrei
Rabbi Shimon, that they come from communal funds from communal funds.
and just like the תמיד Tamid come from communal funds, and that
is רבי שמעון. Reb Shimon. So רבי שמעון Reb Shimon is consistent,
רבי שמעון Reb Shimon in our משנה Mishnah that says the מנחה
Mincha of the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol comes from communal funds if
the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol is dead and there's no substitute. So
he also says that these communal קרבנות, korbanos, these communal קרבנות korbanos
that are, you know, ad hoc, פר העלם דבר של ציבור par
he’elem davar shel tzibbur and the עבודה זרה, avodah zarah, they come
from communal funds, not from special, you know, not from special collections
that are being done, but drawing on the regular communal funds. So
that's what he holds and it might be that this also has
nothing really to do with
negligence, this seems to be based on a פסוק pasuk and therefore
that's why we assume this ברייתא braisa is the authoritative and that
is רבי שמעון. Reb Shimon. So it's רבי יהודה Reb Yehuda that
says you do a special collection, רבי שמעון Reb Shimon that says
you draw on your existing communal funds. Okay, ושלמה תקרב, ushlema tikrav,
back to our משנה. Mishnah.
So our משנה Mishnah said that when there's no כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol and you're bringing this מנחה, Mincha, either from his heirs or
from communal funds, you don't divide it half in the morning, half
in the afternoon, you bring it as an entire unit. So אמר
רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Reb Chiya bar Abba
amar Reb Yochanan, רבי יוחנן Reb Yochanan asked the obvious question that
anybody would ask on this משנה. Mishnah. What did he ask?
שלמה שחרית ושלמה בין הערבים או דילמא שלמה שחרית ובטלה בין הערבים.
shlema shacharis ushlema bein ha'arbaim o dilma shlema shacharis u-vetela bein ha'arbaim.
Do you still bring it in the morning and in the afternoon
and now you just bring a whole סולת soles in the morning
and a whole עישרון issaron in the morning and a whole עישרון
issaron in the afternoon? Or no, you only bring one עישרון issaron
a day, but rather than dividing it into two, you are going
to bring it all together as one in the morning. And we
had פסוקים pesukim that told you it had to be all together.
So אמר רבא, amar Rava, או דילמא שלמה שחרית ובטלה בין הערבים,
o dilma shlema shacharis u-vetela bein ha'arbaim, or maybe you bring it
full in the morning and nothing in the afternoon. אמר רבא תא
שמע, amar Rava ta shma, come on here. שמיני בחביתין, shmini b'chavitin,
that this was talking about how the כהנים kohanim would be divided
in the
different daily עבודה avodah in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and it
said the eighth כהן Kohen would bring the afternoon חביתין chavitin of
the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Okay, that was, you know, between the
מנחה Mincha parts of the תמיד של בין הערבים Tamid shel bein
ha'arbaim in the afternoon, the eighth כהן Kohen would bring the חביתין
chavitin of the כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol.
ואי איתא דבטלה בין הערבים, ve'i issa de-vatela bein ha'arbaim, if there
would be times, you know, when there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol
around that there would be no חביתין chavitin which would be brought,
you know, in the afternoons, הזימנין דלא משכחת לה שמיני בחביתין, hazimnin
d'lo mashkachas la shmini b'chavitin, then how could the משנה Mishnah say
the eighth כהן Kohen would bring the חביתין, chavitin, there wasn't always
חביתין chavitin in the afternoons. So that משנה Mishnah seems to assume
there's always חביתין chavitin in the afternoons, which means even with no
כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, you bring the full עישרון issaron in the
morning and the full עישרון issaron in the afternoon. So is that
a good proof? So the גמרא Gemara says, היכי דמי, heichi dami,
I'm sorry, I ended that too
quickly, היכי דמי דמיית כהן גדול ולא מינו אחר תחתיו? heichi dami
d'meis Kohen Gadol v'lo minu acher tachtav? So if a כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol died and they didn't make a substitute,
if you say that you bring the full עישרון issaron in the
morning and nothing in the afternoon, how could the משנה Mishnah blithely
say the eighth כהן Kohen brings the חביתין? chavitin? All right, by
the way, it means he's bringing it on behalf of the כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, כהן גדול Kohen Gadol still pays for it, but
it's being burnt on the מזבח mizbeach by this eighth כהן. Kohen.
All right, so the fact that it just assumes there's going to
be afternoon חביתין chavitin seems like even when there's no כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, you're going to bring both in the morning and the
afternoon. So that was what רבא Rava said. אמרו רבנן קמיה דרבי
ירמיה, amru rabbanan kamei de-Reb Yirmeya, so the rabbis said it in
front of רבי ירמיה Reb Yirmeya in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael that
here's what רבא Rava says, you bring it in the afternoon, this
is his proof. אמר, amar, he said, famous line in the גמרא,
Gemara, בבלאי טיפשאי, Bavla'ei tipshai, those stupid Babylonians, משום דיתבו בארעא דחשוכא
mishum de-yasvu b'ara de-chashocha because they dwell in a dark land, you
know, it's nearly did not get as much sun as you get
in
Israel, so אמרי שמעתתא דמחשכן, amri shema'ata d'machashchan, they say dark ideas,
you know, they do not say, you know, that's a very שוואך
shvach answer, it's a proof, what type of a proof is that?
That doesn't prove anything. אלא דקתני, ela d'kasani, here I'll show you
that it doesn't prove anything. The משנה Mishnah also says שביעי בסולת
תשיעי ביין, shvi'i b'soles tshi'i b'yayin,
כהן Kohen number seven brings the, you know, the מנחה Mincha of
the תמיד של בין הערבים, Tamid shel bein ha'arbaim, and then כהן
Kohen number eight brings the חביתין, chavitin, the afternoon חביתין chavitin of
the כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, and כהן Kohen number nine brings the
wine of the תמיד של בין הערבים. Tamid shel bein ha'arbaim. Okay,
so now we've also got seven and nine are bringing the מנחה
Mincha and the wine of the תמיד של
בין הערבים. Tamid shel bein ha'arbaim. אהכי נמי דלא בטלי? ahachi nami
d'lo batli? So you would tell me that that can never happen
that it wouldn't get brought, that sometimes it might not get brought?
מנחתם ונסכיהם בלילה מנחתם ונסכיהם אפילו למחר. minchasam v'niskaihem balaila minchasam v'niskaihem
afilu l'machar.
We know that you can bring the מנחה Mincha and the נסכים
nesachim of a קרבן korban if, you know, it's כשר kosher if
you bring it the following night or you bring it even the
next day, so maybe some days it'll happen that you won't have
the מנחה Mincha and the wine for the afternoon
תמיד. Tamid. And so just because the משנה mishna is saying who
gets what doesn't mean it'll never happen that there might not be
an interruption. So he says אלא דאי לא קתני. ela de’i lo
katani. You've got to love that line. What if, you know, kids
will say, "But what if?" What if? We're not teaching. We're not
teaching "what if." We're teaching about the regular rule. The regular rule
is you have the wine, you have the
מנחה, mincha, you have a כהן גדול kohen gadol who's alive, you
have the חביתין chavitin in the afternoon. The משנה mishna is talking
about under normal regular circumstances. Okay, so the fact that it assumes
חביתין chavitin in the afternoon does not prove anything about a "what
if" scenario that there's no כהן גדול. kohen gadol. אזלו קמיה דרבא.
azlu kamei de’Rava. So
the rabbis then went back to רבא Rava and said רבי ירמיה,
Rabbi Yirmeya, here he disagreed with your proof and by the way,
here's what he said, you know, he was really not happy—he said
these nasty words. Okay. אמר, amar, so רבא Rava said מבישותן אמרי
קמייהו מטיבותן לא אמרי קמייהו. mibishutan amri kamaihu mitivutan lo amri kamaihu.
You know, here we are in בבל. Bavel. Sometimes you say ideas,
you throw out ideas. So our not-great ideas, those are the ones
the rabbis go and report in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. Make us
look really bad and they call us like that we say stupid
things. Okay. But they don't report all the brilliant ideas we have
in בבל. Bavel. That, you know, the bad news travels a lot
faster than the good news. People much more take in things that
lead to bad perceptions than to good perceptions. So look at what
you're doing. You are badmouthing, you know, winds up that רבי ירמיה
Rabbi Yirmeya now has this negative perception because you reported this idea.
Fine, it wasn't a great idea. Why aren't people reporting to him
more all the brilliant ideas that I have? Okay. But that seemed
to be a concession that he agreed that, okay, it wasn't a
great proof. והדר אמר רבא, vehadar amar Rava, but then רבא Rava
came back and said הני נמי טיבותן הוו. hanei nami tivutan havu.
You know what? This position I had, it's also one of my
good teachings. Interestingly, not it's a good proof, my position that you
don't bring it, that you bring it in the afternoon, I actually
do hold by that position. Okay. Where do you—אמר קרא, amar kra,
but now I'm not going to get it from the משנה, mishna,
which actually was a bad proof. The משנה mishna was just talking
about standard operating procedure. Here is how I'm going to prove that
you bring it in the afternoon. אמר קרא: סולת מנחה תמיד. amar
kra: solet mincha tamid. הרי היא לך כמנחת תמידים. harei hi lach
ke’minchat tmidim. It says by the חביתין, chavitin, it says it is,
you know, it's flour, a מנחה mincha regular תמיד. tamid. So it
is just like, you know, the מנחה mincha that you bring with
the קרבן תמיד. korban tamid. So just like the קרבן תמיד korban
tamid you are always bringing one in the morning and one in
the afternoon, by the חביתין chavitin also you will always bring morning
and afternoon. So even when there's no כהן גדול kohen gadol and
when you bring it you bring it a full עשרון, issaron, you
will bring an עשרון issaron in the morning and an עשרון issaron
in the afternoon, okay, rather than just one עשרון issaron in the
morning. You do it parallel—when there is a כהן גדול kohen gadol
half and half, when there's no כהן גדול kohen gadol a full
in the morning, a full in the afternoon. מאי הוי עלה? mai
havya alah? What was the upshot about this, about how it's brought
when there's no כהן גדול? kohen gadol? אמר רב נתן בר יצחק:
תא שמע, amar Rav Natan bar Yitzchak: ta shema, come and hear,
דתניא, detanya, it's a ברייתא: braita: שלמה שחרית ושלמה בין הערבים. shlema
shacharit u'shlema bein ha'arbayim. It's a ברייתא. braita. It would be brought
the full עשרון issaron in the morning and a full עשרון issaron
in the afternoon, like רבא Rava taught. Okay. Okay, so now that
we've decided that the full amount that would be brought when there's
no כהן גדול kohen gadol would be a full עשרון issaron in
the morning and a full עשרון issaron in the afternoon, we're now
going to go back to discuss some other specifics of when there
actually was a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, the standard מנחת חביתין minchat
chavitin and how it was brought. So let's take a look. אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbi Yochanan, פליגי
בה אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי ורבנן.
pligi bah Abba
Yossi ben Dostai ve’rabanan. So the following issue is a debate of
אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי Abba Yossi ben Dostai and the rabbis. אבא
יוסי בן דוסתאי אומר: מפריש לה שני קמצים. Abba Yossi ben Dostai
omer: mafrish lah sheni kmatzim. The normal מנחת חביתין, minchat chavitin, which
is one עשרון issaron divided into two halves, you're going to have
two קמצים kmatzim של לבונה, shel levona, two handbreadths of לבונה. levona.
Even though the תורה Torah never says you bring לבונה levona with
it, we assume every מנחה mincha has לבונה, levona, the frankincense brought
with it, with the exception of a מנחת חוטא. minchat chote. Okay.
And the normal amount you bring for לבונה levona is a handful,
a קומץ. komatz. So he says you're going to bring one קומץ
komatz שחרית shacharit and one קומץ komatz בין הערבים, bein ha'arbayim, even
though normally, as we'll see, it's one קומץ komatz for an עשרון,
issaron, for a whole מנחה, mincha, and here you're bringing the קומץ
komatz for half מנחה. mincha. That's his position. קומץ שחרית וקומץ בין
הערבים. komatz shacharit ve'komatz bein ha'arbayim. ורבנן אמרי, ve’rabanan amrei, and the
rabbis say, מפריש לה
קומץ אחד. mafrish lah komatz echad. No, no, no. They say the
same way it's one מנחה mincha divided into two, it's one קומץ
komatz divided into two, one handful of לבונה. levona. חצי קומץ שחרית
וחצי קומץ בין הערבים. chatzi komatz shacharit ve'chatzi komatz bein ha'arbayim. Half
in the morning, half in the afternoon. That seems to make pretty
good sense. במאי קמיפלגי? bemai kamifligi? What is this debate about? אבא
יוסי בן דוסתאי סבר: לא אשכחן חצי קומץ דקריב. Abba Yossi ben
Dostai savar: lo ashchan chatzi komatz de’kariv. אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי Abba
Yossi ben Dostai says, "Look, I, you know, I
can't—we've never found before that you would offer up a half of
a handful of לבונה levona on the מזבח." mizbeach. So yes, it's
also a חידוש chidush that you offer up a half of a...
of a מנחה, mincha, a half of an עשרון. isaron. But nevertheless,
let's not take one חידוש chiddush and go overboard with that. If
there's going to be לבונה, levona, it has to be the normal
amount of לבונה, levona, which is a full handful. Okay, so that's
what he says. A half of a מנחה mincha but a full
handful of לבונה levona in the morning and then the same in
the afternoon. רבנן Rabbanan and the rabbis סברי savri לא אשכחן עשרון
דבעי שני קמצין. lo ashkechan isaron dibaya shnei kmatzin. No,
we never find that one עשרון isaron of סולת solet for a
מנחה mincha gets two handfuls of לבונה. levona. So the whole עשרון
isaron gets one handful, and if you're going to divide the עשרון
isaron morning and afternoon, you'll divide the handful. All right, that to
me seems to make a little bit more sense, but anyway, that's
the debate. Okay, בעי יוחנן. Ba'ei Yochanan. So now רב יוחנן Rav
Yochanan wants to ask a derivative question based on this. כהן גדול
שמת ולא מינו אחר תחתיו, Kohen Gadol shemet velo minu acher tachtav,
the case that we keep on going to. The כהן גדול Kohen
Gadol dies and you don't have a substitute and now you are
going to bring, remember what we decided, a full עשרון isaron in
the morning and a full עשרון isaron in the afternoon. לרבנן, L'Rabbanan,
for the rabbis who say that when it's a half of an
עשרון, isaron, it's a half of a קומץ, kometz, so הוכפלה לבונתו
או לא? huchpela levonato o lo? Now that it's a full עשרון,
isaron, will you double the amount of לבונה? levona? Will you do
a full קומץ, kometz, which makes sense? Full קומץ kometz is the
natural state of things and also it remains the same proportion. If
a half of a קומץ kometz for a half of an עשרון,
isaron, when you go up to a full עשרון, isaron, have a
full קומץ. kometz. Both of those stand to logic. What's the question?
מי אמרינן מתוך שהוכפלה סלתו הוכפלה לבונתו? Mi amrinan mitoch shehuchpela solto
huchpela levonato? Do we say because you doubled the flour you double
the לבונה, levona, which makes sense, keeping the proportions the same and
allowing you to bring a full
קומץ? kometz? או דילמא מאי דגלי גלי מאי דלא גלי לא גלי?
O dilma mai degali gali mai delo gali lo gali? Or do
we say, no, the תורה Torah comes up with a חידוש chiddush
that you're now going to take what was a half of an
עשרון isaron in the morning and make it a full עשרון. isaron.
And that חידוש chiddush is limited to where it says it, to
by the flour. It does not say it by the לבונה. levona.
The לבונה levona remains the same as a half of a קומץ.
kometz. Again, the natural thing would be to want to go up
to a full קומץ, kometz, but that is the question. Now he
does not ask it according to אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי, Abba Yosi
ben Dustai, because אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי Abba Yosi ben Dustai says
that you would bring a full
קומץ kometz even by the half of the מנחה. mincha. So if
you double the מנחה, mincha, you could say okay, let's keep the
proportions the same, a full עשרון isaron brings שני קמצין shnei kmatzin
of לבונה, levona, but that would be very strange to be offering
up שני קמצין shnei kmatzin of
לבונה levona for this offering. So it makes sense to think for
him it would be stable as one קומץ, kometz, but the question
is for רבנן. Rabbanan. Would they take their חצי קומץ khatzi kometz
and make it one to keep the proportion the same and bring
it up to one, or would they keep it stable as a
half?
ושמן, V'shemen, and by the way, I have another question. Okay, by
the oil, בין לאבא יוסי בן דוסתאי בין לרבנן מהו? bein l'Abba
Yosi ben Dustai bein l'Rabbanan mahu? Similarly, if you have this scenario
where the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol dies and you're bringing a full
measure, so when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol was around you brought
one עשרון isaron of סולת solet and we said before three לוג
log of oil, and then you would divide it, half in the
morning half in the afternoon, so a half of an עשרון isaron
with one and a half לוג log of oil, still a one
to three ratio. Now there's no כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and you're
going to bring a full עשרון isaron of flour. What are you
going to do in terms of the oil? Are you going to
now keep the proportions and have each morning, the morning full עשרון,
isaron, three לוג, log, afternoon full עשרון, isaron, three לוג, log, or
are you going to keep everything else stable and keep the oil
at one and a half? So even though now you have a
full עשרון isaron in the morning, you'll still have only one and
a half לוג log of oil. Okay, and that has nothing to
do with the debate of אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי Abba Yosi ben
Dustai and רבנן; Rabbanan; they were just debating the amount of the
קמצין, kmatzin, but this is a separate question: are you going to
change the proportions or not for the oil? Are you going to
keep the proportions the same and therefore double the amount of oil
when you're doubling
the flour or keep the oil the same and keep it at
the same one and a half level.
תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, תא
שמע, ta shema, come and hear. ה' קמצין הן. Heh kmatzin hen.
Okay, so this is a teaching later on in a משנה Mishna
that says there are five times there's a קומץ kometz comes up
in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. All right, and it gives the
various times,
the קומץ kometz of the לבונה levona and the קומץ kometz of
the מנחה mincha and so on. Now one of the
things it does not say there is, it does not give the
one of the קמצין kmatzin as the קומץ kometz of לבונה levona
that would come with the חביתי כהן גדול. Chavitei Kohen Gadol. Now
the reason is because in a standard case of חביתי כהן גדול,
Chavitei Kohen Gadol, that קומץ kometz would come in halves, half in
the morning half in the afternoon, and we're not talking about halves,
we're only talking about when the קומץ kometz would come together. But
now he is saying ואי איתא, v'ee ita, but if it would
happen that when the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol wasn't around You would
bring
a full קומץ kometz in the morning and a full קומץ kometz
in the afternoon of the לבונה, levonah, so ואם איתא, ve'im isa,
זימנין דמשכחת ליה שבעה, zimnin d'mashkachat lei shiva,
so sometimes you'll have, you know, seven קמצים kmatzim because your normal
five and now that there's no כהן גדול, kohen gadol, you have
a קומץ kometz of the לבונה levonah in the morning and a
קומץ kometz of the לבונה levonah in the afternoon. So the fact
that it doesn't give that case shows that it is, you know,
shows number one, it's following the rabbis and it's assuming that you
only have in a normal case of a כהן גדול, kohen gadol,
only half of a קומץ kometz in the morning and half of
an afternoon, and it's showing that in accordance with the rabbis when
there's no כהן גדול, kohen gadol, it remains half in the morning
and half in the afternoon even though the amount of flour has
now doubled, the קומץ kometz of לבונה levonah will always remain half
in the morning and half in the afternoon, because if that wasn't
the case, it should have said that you can come up with
seven קמצים kmatzim when there's no כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So the
גמרא Gemara says what it said before, now דאי לא תני, d'i
lo tani,
what if it's not teaching? It's not teaching not normal cases, it's
talking standard cases. You know, so it's an aberration when there's no
כהן גדול. kohen gadol. So it doesn't prove what you would do
or not and it could be when there is no כהן גדול,
kohen gadol, you would bring a full amount. But that משנה mishna
does indicate like the rabbis against אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי, Abba Yossi
ben Dostai, that when there is a כהן גדול, kohen gadol, you
only bring a half amount, because otherwise it should have mentioned it.
Okay, יתיב רב פפא קמיה דהא שמעתא, yasiv Rav Pappa kama d'ha
shma'ata, Rav Pappa was sitting and selling over this discussion. אמר ליה
רב יוסף בר שמעיה לרב פפא, amar lei Rav Yosef bar Shmaya
l'Rav Pappa, Rav Yosef bar Shmaya said to Rav Pappa, והמעלה קומץ
בחוץ, veha ma'aleh kometz bachutz, wait a minute, what do you mean
that it says it doesn't speak about aberrant cases? One of the
קמצים kmatzim that it says in that משנה mishna is somebody who
offers up a קומץ kometz of a מנחה mincha outside of the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash that you're חייב chayav for העלאת חוץ. ha'alas
chutz. That is not standard operating procedure. Okay, דאי הוה, d'i hava,
that's a case of what if, that's an aberrant case, וקתני, vekatani,
and it teaches it. So therefore it seems to me that it
is a good argument that the משנה mishna is teaching all cases
of קומץ kometz even if they're not standard. And the fact that
it never gives the קומץ kometz of the חביתין chavitim of the
כהן גדול kohen gadol indicates that a כהן גדול kohen gadol normally
would only be a half and a half, and even when there
was no כהן גדול kohen gadol and you doubled the flour, it
would remain a half and a half. Okay, seems like a pretty
good proof. So the גמרא Gemara says, but you know, it's not
explicit, so we're not yet concluding. So מאי הוה עלה, mai hava
alah, what was the ultimate decision, you know, upshot of this? So
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, תא שמע,
ta shma, come and hear, דתניא, d'tanya, we taught a ברייתא. braisa.
כהן גדול שמת, kohen gadol she-meis, our case, ולא מינו אחר תחתיו,
velo minu acher tachtav, he died, you don't have a substitute.
שלימה שחרית ושלימה בין הערבים, sheleima shacharis vesheleima bein ha'arbayim, we quoted
that before. That's how we resolved the earlier issue, the full amount
of flour in the morning, the full amount of flour in the
afternoon. ומפריש לה בי קמצים, u-mafrisha bei kmatzim, and you have two
קמצים kmatzim of
לבונה, levonah, קומץ שחרית וקומץ בין הערבים, kometz shacharis vekometz bein ha'arbayim,
the קומץ kometz in the morning and the קומץ kometz in the
afternoon. Okay, now we don't know if this is going like the
חכמים chachamim or אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי, Abba Yossi ben Dostai, we'll
get to that. ומפריש לה שלשה לוגין, u-mafrisha shlosha lugin, and you
have three לוגין lugin of oil, לוג ומחצה שחרית ולוג ומחצה בין
הערבים, log ve-chevtza shacharis ve-log ve-chevtza bein ha'arbayim, and a half and
a half in the morning, one and a half in the afternoon.
All right, so now you've doubled the flour because there's no כהן
גדול, kohen gadol, but the oil is stable, you're only keeping it
at one and a half at each. So let's see what we
can infer from this. מני, mani, who is this ברייתא braisa going
like?
אילימא רבנן, ileima rabanan, if it's the rabbis that say that in
a normal case of a כהן גדול kohen gadol it would be
a half קומץ kometz in the morning and a half in the
afternoon of the לבונה, levonah, so מאי שנא לבונה דהוכפלה, mai shna
levonah d'huchpela, but this ברייתא braisa is saying when there's no כהן
גדול kohen gadol it's a full קומץ. kometz. So why would that
be that we would double the לבונה levonah to keep the proportions
the same, מאי שנא לבונה דהוכפלה מאי שנא שמן דלא הוכפלה, mai
shna levonah d'huchpela mai shna shemen d'lo huchpela, but we wouldn't double
the oil? Remember, it's very clear the oil is stable, one and
a half לוג log in the morning even though it's now a
full סולת soles in the morning, so the oil stays stable. So
why are we, would we keep the oil stable but double the
לבונה? levonah? That doesn't make any sense, it really doesn't. You could
say we want to double the לבונה levonah to get a full
קומץ, kometz, but we would want to double the oil to get
a full three לוגין, lugin, a לוג log and a half is
not normally a meaningful measurement. So clearly this can't be the rabbis,
because if it was the rabbis, if it's going to be stable
oil, it would be stable לבונה levonah and it would only be
half of a קומץ. kometz. אלא, ela, it must be אבא יוסי
בן דוסתאי, Abba Yossi ben Dostai, it's אבא יוסי בן דוסתאי Abba
Yossi ben Dostai he, דאמר חביתי כהן גדול בעלמא שני קמצים בעיא.
d'amar chavitei kohen gadol be'alma shnei kmatzim ba'ya. Okay, that would say
that no, normally even when the כהן גדול kohen gadol is around,
a full קומץ kometz in the morning, a full קומץ kometz in
the afternoon. Okay, and therefore it works, you double the flour, okay,
when there's no כהן גדול, kohen gadol, ולבונה לא הוכפלה, ve-levonah lo
huchpela, the לבונה's levonah a full קומץ, kometz, that's stable, that was
it, what it would have been even when there was
a כהן גדול. kohen gadol. That actually works very nicely according to
רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי. Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai. So what does that
show us? So, השתא דאמר רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי, hashtah de'amar Rabbi
Yosi Ben Dustai, ולבונה לא הוכפלה ושמן לא הוכפל, velivona lo huchpala
veshemen lo huchpal, ומדשמן לאבא יוסי בן דוסתאי לא הוכפלה, umid'shemen l'Abba
Yosi Ben Dustai lo huchpalah, לבונה
ושמנה לרבנן נמי לא הוכפלו. levontah v'shmanah lerabbanan nami lo huchpalu. So
the only debate of יוסי בן דוסתאי Yosi Ben Dustai and the
Rabbis was what's the normal amount that you do for the לבונה
levona for a כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. But other issues about what
happens when there's no כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, there's no basis to
think they debate. So since we are seeing that for רבי יוסי
בן דוסתאי Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai that even when there's no כהן
גדול Kohen Gadol and you double the flour, you have a full
עשרון, isaron, you keep the oil and the לבונה levona stable, we
should assume that the same will be true for the Rabbis. That's
a pretty reasonable argument. So therefore the Rabbis and רבי יוסי בן
דוסתאי Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai argue when there is a כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, half of a קומץ kometz and half of a קומץ
kometz for the Rabbis of לבונה levona or full and full for
יוסי בן דוסתאי, Yosi Ben Dustai, but when there's no כהן גדול,
Kohen Gadol, then you keep the flour double, but you keep the
לבונה levona stable, so you keep it at a half for the
Rabbis and at a full for רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי, Rabbi Yosi
Ben Dustai, and you keep the oil stable at one and a
half לוג. log. Okay. אמר
רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan, so now to wrap this up, הלכה
כרבי יוסי בן דוסתאי. halacha k'Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai. We rule like
רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai that it would be
a full קומץ kometz in the morning, a full in the afternoon.
Of course תוספות Tosafot says: תימה הלכתא למשיחא? Teima, hilchata lemashiach? What
do you mean הלכה? halacha? We're פוסק-ing pasken for the time of
משיח? Mashiach? I mean, you know, it's one thing to debate the
principles and what are they arguing about, but what does it mean
to פוסק pasken הלכה? halacha? Okay, but anyway that's what he says.
ומי אמר רבי יוחנן הכי? U'mi amar Rabbi Yochanan hachi? Did רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan really say that? ואמר רבי יוחנן הלכה כסתם משנה.
V'amar Rabbi Yochanan halacha k'stam Mishna. We normally, the teaching is we
go like a סתם משנה. stam Mishna. תנן חמישה קמצים הם, Tnan,
chamisha kmatzim hem, and it says there are five קמצים. kmatzim. And
for רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי, Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai, right, even a
normal חביתי כהן גדול chavitei Kohen Gadol would have a קומץ kometz
in the morning of לבונה levona and a קומץ kometz in the
afternoon, so for him it should have been seven. So how, so
that משנה, Mishna, סתם משנה stam Mishna is the רבנן. Rabbanan. So
how could he פוסק pasken we go like רבי יוסי בן דוסתאי?
Rabbi Yosi Ben Dustai? So the גמרא Gemara says: אמוראי נינהו אליבא
דרבי יוחנן. Amoraim ninhu aliba d'Rabbi Yochanan. There's a debate of אמוראים.
Amoraim. One אמורא Amora thinks that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says we
always go by a סתם משנה, stam Mishna, that's a pretty important
opinion, the גמרא Gemara usually accepts it. The אמורא Amora who says
that רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan is ruling like יוסי בן דוסתאי Yosi
Ben Dustai assumes that we don't always go according to רבי יוחנן,
Rabbi Yochanan, it's not true we don't always go like a סתם
משנה. stam Mishna. Very good, so we will end with that with
the discussion of חביתי כהן גדול. chavitei Kohen Gadol. הדרן עלך התכלת,
Hadran alach hatchelet, we will end here for today.